Guide to the Jewish Communal Registers (Pinkese kehilah) Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Inventory, 1623-1960
  - Pinkas: mi-bet tefilah he-hadash, 1892 (Box 16)
    Ramnicu-Sarat, Romania. Lavishly illuminated pages with ink borders and calligraphy. Original leather cover with title and depiction of the ten commandments in gold ink. Includes pages in honor of contributors and by-laws of the synagogue. Guidelines for synagogue decorum, such as "...drinking in the synagogue is permitted only on the festival of Simhat Torah..." and "one may not enter the synagogue with a cane or an umbrella." The register contains testimony of the community's rabbi concerning girls who were mukot ets, e.g. who lost their virginity through an accidental injury, not by rape. There is also an account of a miracle that befell the community when the synagogue was saved from hostile townspeople's attempts to destroy it. In Hebrew.
  - Hevrah Tehilim Bikur holim u-mishmorim Bet ha-Keneset Stefeni Ortodoks, 1920-1924 (Box 17)
    London. Illuminated title page. By-laws of a society of theStepney Orthodox Synagogue, including rules governing use of the society's gold, silver, and ornamental items. Scribe's rule marks are visible in margins. In Yiddish.
  - [Pinkas kehilat Mantovah], 5384, [1623-1624] (Box 18)
    Mantua, Italy. The register contains lists of local yeshivot, decisions of the community council, and accounts of events that took place in the community in the beginning of the seventeenth century. This appears to be a rare document that was saved from the destruction of the ghetto and expulsion of the Jews during the war of 1629-30 (see Shlomo Simonsohn's History of the Jews in the Duchy of Mantua). In Hebrew. Original marbled paper cover. 26 leaves; 31 cm.
  - Protocoll der is. cult. Gemeinde; [Pinkas Mishkolts], [vol. 1] 1808-1835, [vol. 2] 1851-1852 (Box 18)
    Miskolc, Hungary. Communal registers (two volumes), including regulations, customs, matters before the community board, appointments of rabbis and others serving the Jewish community \(mesharetim ba-kodesh\), and the establishment of social welfare societies, as well as descriptions of historical events in Miskolc. In Hebrew and Yiddish, with title on cover in German and on spine in Hungarian. 40, 43 cm.,. This item has been microfilmed; see film HM 271-1.
  - Be-asarah maamarot nivra ha-olam; [Pinkas hevrat "Ozer Dalim"], 5657-673, [1897-1913] (Box 19)
    Yerushalayim.Register containing the ten by-laws of the Ozer Dalim Society in Jerusalem, which dealt with helping the poor and honoring the dead. The society accepted these obligations in honor of the patrons and founders of the society, R. Shabtai Fintsi and his wife, Flor di Fintsi. The register also contains minutes of meetings recording debates and decisions of the community's board, signed by its leaders. In Ladino and Hebrew. [16] pp. with additional small pages attached; 33 cm.
  - Kaasher raoh rainu anaḥnu ha-ḥ.m. et ha-ḥ.ḳ. shelanu Ḥosen Yeshuot...; [Vilna: pinkas hevrat Hosen Yeshuot], 1872-1899 (Box 19)
    Vilna. Register of the charitable Hosen Yeshuot Society, including by-laws, lists of members and contributors, and memorial pages. In Hebrew, with illuminated headings and title pages. Approx. 70 leaves; ill.: 36 cm.
  - Pinḳas ha-niḳra bi-leshon Ashkenaz proṭoḳol; [Csaba: pinkas kehilah], 1830-1890 (Box 19)
    Csaba, Hungary. Communal register, including by-laws, minutes of meetings, records of income and expenditures. In Yiddish, Hebrew and Hungarian. 134 leaves; 40 cm.,. This item has been microfilmed; see film HM 271-2.
  - Sefer hazkarat neshamot, 1922 (Box 20)
    Galatz [Romania]. Memorial book from community of Galaţi, Romania. Includes pages in memory of Theodor Herzl and men who were killed in World War I, as well as other men and women in the Jewish community. In Hebrew, with title page and engraved metal plaque on cover in Hebrew and German. Title page illuminated with gold and colored inks. [33] leaves; 38 cm.
  - [Galaţi, Romania: Register book of the Jewish community]; [Pinkas kehilat Galatz], 1921-1923 (Box 20)
    Bound collection of documents, mainly in Romanian, with manuscript on vellum in Yiddish. 1 vol.; 35 cm.
  - Pinkas shel ha-hevra kadishah K.K. Geviler, 1820-1860 (Box 21)
    Guebwiller, France. Register of a Jewish welfare society of the community of Guebwiller, a town in the Alsace region in southeastern France. Includes by-laws of the community, as well as lists of members and contributions. In Hebrew, Yiddish and French, with original binding. 36 leaves; 22 cm.
  - Sterf-register der Nederlansch Israelitische Gemeente te Alphen, 1823-1940 (Box 21)
    Alphen aan den Rijn. Death-register of the Dutch-Jewish congregation in a small Jewish community in the province of Zuid-Holland, the Netherlands. Entries list names of deceased members, names of spouses, places and dates of death, and ages at death. In Dutch, with some names and dates written in Hebrew. [129] pp.; 33 cm.
  - Mlada Boleslav: pinkese kehilah, 1785-1798 (Box 22)
    Mlada Boleslav, also known as Jungbunzlau or Bumsla, in Northern Bohemia. Minutes of meetings of the Jewish community council concerning the rabbi, taxes, and other communal matters. Manuscripts, mainly in German, with many of the signatures in Hebrew. Includes numerous documents with signatures of women, such as "Rahel eshet R. Eliezer Bondi." 2 vols. (over 250 pp.); 36 cm.
  - Zeh ha-pinḳas shayakh leha-ḥavurah mishnayot de-ḳeloiz poh ḳ.ḳ. Mihaloṿits...; [Pinkas Mihalovits], 1925-1934 (Box 23)
    Michalovce/Nagymihaly, Slovakia. Communal register of Mishnah society from the Jewish community near the Slovakian-Hungarian border. Includes by-laws of the society and names of members, with the dates for members who joined or died after the society was established. Manuscript in Hebrew. Approx. 80 pp. with writing; 30 cm.
  - Pinkas me-hevrah mishnayot me-Nyu Britn Konn. / maase yede oman he-ḥaver Shemuel be-R. Aharon Yitsḥaḳ Margolin, 682, [1921-1922]-689, [1928-1929] (Box 23)
    Cover title: Pinkas me-ḥevrah mishnayot shel ha-talmud torah de-Nyu Briṭin, Ḳonn. New Britain, Connecticut. Communal register of Mishnah society, including by-laws, names of members, and contributions. Hand-colored title page, illuminated by Samuel Margolin. 1 v. (approx. 20 pp. with writing); 37 cm.
  - Stammbuch uber die durch die mediascher orth. chevra-kadisa verwaleten stiftungen (keren kajemes); [Pinḳas Orṭhodoḳs Ḥevra Ḳadisha Mediash], 1927-1940 (Box 24)
    Medias, Romania. Register of the social welfare committee. Printed register with approximately seventy pages filled in by hand. In German and Yiddish. 47 cm.
  - Pinkas de-hevrah mishnayot im halukat ha-Sha"s, 640, [1884-1885] (Box 25)
    Yerushalayim. Communal register of the most important synagogue in the old city of Jerusalem, Hurbat R. Yehudah he-Hasid. Includes three pages of by-laws, about twenty pages of names of the men and women in the society, and also approximately eleven pages of names of women with the "conditions" of their entry into the society: financial contributions, prayers, and other customs of the society. These conditions were signed by rabbinic leaders of Jerusalem, including: R. Yehudah Hilman, author of 666 [1906], R. Avraham Yaakov Shubatski and R. Yitshak Aizik Yafah, a leader of the Vilna Seminary. In Hebrew. 34 pp.; 39 cm.
  - Ketav-yad pinkas K.K. Shats, 1852-1960 (Box 26)
    Shats (Suceava, Romania). Register of social welfare society. Romania. Includes memorial prayers and names of members of the community with dates of their deaths. Manuscript in Hebrew on vellum, with decorative border on first page in sepia ink. Purchased together with women's register (see: Froyen-grindungs-mitglieder shel hevrah g.h.: I.\). In Hebrew. 11 pp.; 27 x 28 cm.
  - Froyen-grindungs-mitglieder shel hevrah g.h.: I., 1907-1959 (Box 26)
    Shats (Suceava, Romania). Register of women's society for gemilut hasadim ("acts of lovingkindness"). Includes memorial prayer and names of members of the society with dates of their deaths. Some of the names of the women's fathers are listed in Ketav-yad pinkas K.K. Shats. Manuscript in Hebrew on paper. Purchased together with Ketav-yad pinkas K.K. Shats. 7 pp.; 22 x 25 cm.
  - Hevrah mishnayot anshe Maramarish, 685, [1924-1925]-1960 (Box 26)
    Sighet, Romania? Communal register. Manuscript in Hebrew. Decorative title page. Names of members written in gold and colored ink on individual pages, with dates of death added where appropriate. Includes alphabetical indexes of names of men and women, and chronological lists of the deceased. Although the title page identifies this register with "the Mishnayot Society of the People of Maramarish," founded in 685 [1924 or 1925], the dates of deaths listed are mainly from the post-war years to 1960. The blank register was manufactured in New York, which suggests that it may contain the records of an American group with roots in Sighet. 1 vol.; 37 cm.
  - [Tata, Hungary: Pinkas hevrah kadisha]; A tabi ḥevrah ḳadisha Jegyzokonyve; A tabi Chevrah Kadisa, 1912-1944 (Box 26)
    Tata, Hungary. Manuscript register of communal welfare society. Includes history of community from 1769, by-laws of the Hevrah Kadishah, and descriptions of various issues, concerns, and activities of the community. 253 pp.; 34 cm.
  - Sefer ha-zikhronot divre ha-yamim, [1790-1801?] (Box 27)
    Györ, Hungary. Register from the Jewish community of Raab, now known as Gy¨or, on the northwestern border of Hungary. Includes historical records of institutions such as the hevrah kadisha, communal meetings, and decisions dating back to the late eighteenth century. Title page has note signed in 1897 by rabbi and head of the rabbinical court of Gy¨or and Gy¨or-Sziget, Gyula Fischer \("Ha-sefer ha-zeh matsanu bi-shenat 1897 Shalom Yehudah Fisher"\). In Hebrew, Yiddish, and German. 10 pp.; 43 cm.
  - 1891-1901 Jegyzökönyv...; Pinkas de-K.K. Gyor (Box 27)
    Györ, Hungary. Communal register from the Jewish community of Raab, now known as Györ, on the northwestern border of Hungary, in honor of ten years of leadership of the community by Dr. Pfeiffer Fülöp. Includes descriptions of communal institutions and needs that he attended to. Title page includes an exceptional color illustration signed by Rajz. Förstner Tivadar. Pages written on heavyweight cardboard. In Hungarian. 14 pp.; ill., 40 cm.
  - Sefer zikhronot, 679, [1918-1919] (Box 27)
    Hungary. Memorial book from a Jewish community in Hungary(?)--town not given. Includes memorial prayers and separate lists of names of men and women. Title page illuminated with colored paints. Cover has design in gold and silver ink. In Hebrew. [8] pp.; 44 cm.
  - Pinkas Papa, 1872-1943 (Box 27)
    Papa, Hungary. Manuscript register from the Hevrah Bikur Holim, a Jewish communal welfare society. Includes detailed accounts of income and expenses with names of contributors and recipients. Records from 1872 to 1911 written in Yiddish and from 1911 to 1943 in Hungarian. [252, 72] pp.; 42 cm.,. This item has been microfilmed; see film HM 271-3.
  - Pinḳas ha-laz shayakh le-H.H. ha-alufim Ro.Ṭ. manhige ḳehilatenu K.K. Palaṭi... /Ḳahal Adat Yeshurun., 575, [1814-1815] (Box 28)
    Palati (Palota?), Romania. Register of Jewish community. Manuscript in Hebrew and Romanian. Title page illuminated with colored paints. Original leather cover. 1 vol. (approx. 100 pp. with writing); 34 cm.
  - Ha-pinḳas ha-laz shayakh leha-ḥevrah ḳedoshah de-ḳ.ḳ. p. Ardoya...; [Pinkas takanot u-minhage kehilat Ardovo]; o, 623, [1862-1863] (Box 28)
    On cover: "Naaśah ṿe-nigmar... a.y.... Yosef Daṿid.": Ardovo, Slovakia. Communal register from the Jewish community of Ardovo in southern Slovakia. This manuscript includes eighteen pages of by-laws of the community; six pages of decisions and additions to those regulations signed by famous rabbis, including Mordekhai ha-Levi Horovits; and forty pages listing names of members. Half of the by-laws are written in Hebrew and half in Yiddish. Section headings:. 1 vol.; 36 x 26 cm.
  - Hathalat ha-protokollen min shenat 687… de-ḥevra mishnayot ṿe-talmud torah ba-ir Mishḳolts; Protoḳoll bukh shel ha-ḥevra mishnayot ṿe-talmud torah; Jegyzökönyv, 687, [1926-1927]-1944 (Box 28)
    Miskolc, Hungary. Minutes of meetings of school board of Jewish community. Minutes from 1927-1942 written in Yiddish or Judeo-German, 1942-1944 written in Hungarian. Some pages missing or damaged. 1 vol.; 34 cm.
  - [Account book of Ezras Torah Organization], 1922-1927 (Box 29)
    New York. Register of income and expenditures of Ezras Torah, a Jewish philanthropic organization founded in 1915 by the Union of Orthodox Rabbis. Includes lists of contributors and recipients. Manuscript in Hebrew. 400 pp.; 36 cm.
  - Haupt Protokoll für Gemeinde Palota, 1825-1884 (Box 30)
    Palota, Romania(?). Description from auction catalog: "Pinkas of the small Jewish community of Palota, from 1826-1866 in Hebrew and Yiddish, and from 1867-1884 in German, Polish [sic], and Yiddish...various hands, original leather engraved in German 'Haupt Protokolle des Gemeinde Palota.' An important historical manuscript relating to the religious life of Jews in the small Polish hamlet of Palota." According to the vendor, this communal register comes from the same village as another one identified with Palati or Palota in Romania, (see: Pinḳas ha-laz shayakh le-H.H. ha-alufim Ro.Ṭ. manhige ḳehilatenu K.K. Palaṭi...\). Not determined if they are from the same place or from different villages with similar names. 430 pp.; 40 cm.
  - [Seven pinkese kehilah (community record books)]; [Pinḳese ḳehilot Ḳushṭa ṿe-Izmir] (Box 30)
    Constantinople, Smyrna. Description of contents based on material written by Dov Cohen and provided by the vendor, Yeshayahu Vinograd: seven registers from two of the most important communities in the Ottoman Empire: Constantinople (Istanbul), and Smyrna. The registers are an important source of information about life in these communities in the period 1883-1949, just prior to the decline of these communities. The information relates to a variety of areas, including economics, society, religion, and marital status.
  - Book of the proceedings of the Va'ad ha-ḳehilah in Smyrna, 1928 March 16-1931 June 28 (Box 31)
    The register describes the proceedings of the Va'ad Ha-kehilah (community council) meetings, including the names of participants, the topics discussed and the decisions made. The register is a faithful reflection of the day-to-day life in the community at that time. It deals with a variety of areas, such as the community's social, religious, educational and welfare institutions, community elections, support of the poor, disputes in the community, the relationship with the Ashkenazic community, etc. Approx. 200 pp.; 20 x 31 cm.
  - Two registers containing copies of certificates and letters sent by the Vaad ha-ḳehilah (community council) of the Galata-Phira Quarter in Constantinople, 1913 May 15-1919 August 5, 1920 July-1921 April (Box 31)
    These registers contain close to one thousand assorted certificates pertaining to the Jews of Constantinople, including certificates of good character, death certificates, emigration certificates from Constantinople to other countries, family composition, the establishment of synagogues, support for orphans and the poor, World War I refugees, orphans, widows, and so on. Among the copies are a few original certificates. Some of the letters are addressed to famous personalities, such as R. Chaim Nachum, rabbi of Turkey; R. Refael Saban; and others. In Ladino (Hebrew characters) and French. 2 vols., 500 pp., 514 pp.; 28 cm.
  - Inventory book of the synagogues in Smyrna, 1949 (Box 31)
    A detailed list of the contents of the synagogues in Smyrna in 1949. This is an important register that documents religious and ceremonial life in the Smyrna community at the end of its golden age, just before most of its members immigrated to Israel. The register lists every single item in the synagogues, such as the number of Torah scrolls, ark curtains, silver trays, Torah pointers, carpets, menorahs, chandeliers, and so on. Ladino in Latin characters. 30 pp.; 24 cm.
  - Three account books of the Constantinople community, 1883-1885, 1888-1891, 1894-1900 (Box 32–33)
    These registers include the financial balances of the community and listings of revenues and outlays. The revenues include loans from various individuals, marriage taxes, meat taxes, burial taxes, etc. Outlays include support of widows, orphans, and the poor; salaries of the chief rabbi; the rabbinical court; and schools. 3 v. (Sivan 1883-Elul 1885, 80 pp.; Tamuz 1888-Sivan 1891, 157 pp.; January 1894-December 1900, 161 pp.); 41 cm.
  - [Frankfurt Jewish community: collection of documents from the eighteenth century] (Box 33)
    Frankfurt, Germany. Collection of Jewish communal records from the eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. Manuscripts in Yiddish, German, and Judeo-German. Description of contents based on material provided by the vendor, Bery Gross.
  - Pinkas: Frankfurt. Account book of salaries for the rabbi, judges and kosher butchers, 1798-1809 (Box 34)
    Payment for other services, e.g. for renting the house from the rabbi, etc. Mainly in Hebrew script, but payments to Germans listed in back of register in German. 18 cm.
  - Ledger of contractor dealing with people of Frankfurt, Hanau and Darmstadt, with regulations concerning payments, undated (Box 34)
    Names of prominent families cited. 22 cm.
  - Pinkas Frankfurt. Charities for the poor people from Eretz Israel, 1738-1805 (Box 34)
    Names of important emissaries from Jerusalem, Tiberias, Safed, etc. are cited. Expenses, such as hiring of servants of emissaries. Charities for other purposes as well, such as to help the healing of the rabbi. 40 cm.
  - Register for tax appraisers, 1785-1804 (Box 34)
    Cover date: 555 [1794-1795]. 35 cm.
  - Accounts of the Talmud Torah school, Frankfurt, 1777-1778 (Box 34)
    Account book for dues, donations, funds expended for various needs of the students. List of names of students and families. 34 cm.
  - Receipt book, [1783?] (Box 34)
    10 x 18 cm.
  - Folio des Steuerregisters [receipt book], 1842 (Box 34)
    10 x 17 cm.
  - Miscellaneous documents and letters (nine)., [ca.1800?] (Box 34)
  - [Pinkas from Beirut], 1910-1915 (Box 35)
    Cover title: Copie de lettres. Beirut. Jewish communal register, containing records of meetings and decisions by the community council, names of members of the community, and communications with governmental authorities of Lebanon and Palestine, rabbinical courts and other communities. In French. 500 pp.; 28 cm.
- Additional material, 1775-1941; Accession 2008-M-042
  - Protokoll ... / orth. Chewra Kadischa in Medgyes; [Pinḳas proṭoḳolim shel Ḥevrah Ḳadisha (Szent-Egylet), Medgyes], 1904-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Medias, Romania. Register book from the Hevra Kadisha, social welfare society, of the town of Medias (Medgyes) in northwestern Romania. Includes minutes of meetings and reports of the Hevra Kadisha, with official stamps and signatures of the rabbis and officers. Mainly in German, with some Romanian and Hungarian. 2 v.; 35 cm.
  - Zeh ha-pinḳas de-ḥevra ḳadisha le-alufe, gabae, manhige ḳehal Adat Yeshurun poh ḳ.ḳ. Irsha. Ḥeshbon bukh ... ḥevra ḳadisha, 1822-1875 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Alberti-Irsa, Hungary. Account book of the Ḥevra ḳadisha of Irsa, Hungary, a social welfare society whose members were leaders of the Jewish community. Annual accounts, including names of donors and recipients; amounts received and spent; and description of transactions. Manuscript, mainly in Yiddish, with some Hebrew. Title page calligraphed and illuminated with colored and gold ink. Original leather and marbled binding, repaired with tape over spine. Cover title partially worn off. [180] p.; 38 cm.
  - Pinḳas agudat nashim be-Ṿinah, 1880-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Cover title: Protokoll. [Vienna: minutes of a Jewish women's society, 1880-1921]. Floridsdorf (Vienna, Austria). Description based on material provided by vendor, Moshe Rosenfeld: minutes of meetings of the Israelitische Frauen-Verein, the Jewish women's society from the Floridsdorf district of Vienna, Austria, documenting the involvement of women in the social welfare activities of the Jewish community. The minutes are signed by the women on the board of the society, and sometimes by the rabbi, Dr. J.S. Bloch, or a lay leader of the community. Topics mentioned include: collection and disbursement of charitable funds, caring for the sick and needy, support for orphans and widows, support for communal institutions, and rules of conduct for women. Manuscript in German. [221 p.]; 37 cm.
  - Sefer ha-zikaron: bo yipaḳed shemot kol ha-nifṭarim ume-elaṿ yiḳare yom alotam el ginze meromim / nitḳan al yede ha-ṿaad manhige ha-ḳehilah ṿe-hekhal ha-tefilah de-poh Ḳ.Ḳ. Ḳampina; Cartea pentru Pomenirea Decedaţilor, 1912-1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Campina, Romania. Memorial book from the Jewish community of Campina, Romania, inscribed with memorial prayers, names of leaders of the community, and the names and yahrzeits (anniversaries of deaths) of the community's men (p. 5-33) and women (p. 52-65). Original leather binding with title, spine decoration and geometric border embossed in gold ink. Heavyweight pages with names of deceased members of the community and their dates of death calligraphed inside printed black borders. Manuscript in Hebrew. Covers and title pages in Hebrew and Romanian. 100 leaves (46 filled in); 34 cm.
  - Pinḳas ha-gadol me-ḥevrat linat ha-tsedeḳ u-viḳur ḥolim be-tokhekhe Yerushalayim; Pinḳas ḥevrat linat ha-tsedek u-vikur ḥolim, 658 [1897 or 1898] (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Jerusalem. Communal register of a social welfare society providing aid for the ill and needy in Jerusalem, founded by the ultra-Orthodox Hungarian community, "Kolel Ungarn," [p. 2] -- אלה התקנות אשר לחברת לינת הצדק וביקור חולים הנוסדה ע"י חסידי בית המדרש "אוהל יצחק" אשר לכולל אונגארין Manuscript with calligraphy in black, red, green and gold ink. Headings in block letters and text in Rashi script. Decorative, stamped borders on title pages and introduction. Ten pages of by-laws of the society written in Hebrew and Yiddish, followed by pages with names of members, men and women. Women's section has title: Shaar ezrat nashim ha-menuyot le-ḥevratenu ha-ḳ. = 'שער עזרת נשים המנויות לחברתינו הק. One vol.; 37 cm.
  - Taḳanot shel ḥavurah mishnayot de-poh ḳ.ḳ. Mediash. [Pinḳas ḥevrah mishnayot Mediash], 681 [1921] (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Medias, Romania. Register of Mishnah society of the Jewish community of Medias, Romania. Three pages of by-laws of the society, followed by pages inscribed with the Hebrew names of the members, including both the father's and the mother's names, and a pencil illustration, "Într-o casă religioasă din Germania, desen de: Gidali Nandor." Manuscript in Hebrew, with some Romanian and Yiddish. 22 x 30 cm.
  - Ḳunṭeret shel mazkir neshamot, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Üdveert [Hungary] ? Memorial book from Jewish community of Üdveert, Hungary (?). Title page in red, gold and black ink, followed by memorial pages with the names of members of the community. Names written in large Hebrew calligraphy and also in Hungarian. Unlike other registers in the collection, names of women are interspersed with the men's names, often on the same page as their husband. An unrelated printed page inserted into this volume appears to be a bill of sale of leaven for the duration of Passover. Manuscript in Hebrew and Hungarian. 31 cm.
  - Notulen boek der pieuse vereeniging, Aṭeret baḥurim gemilut ḥasadim te Borculo, 1896-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)